<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Go on Blog by Ekta</title>
    <link>https://blog.ektagarg.com/tags/go/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Go on Blog by Ekta</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 03 Jan 2021 11:58:58 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://blog.ektagarg.com/tags/go/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Profiling and optimizing GO [PART-1]</title>
      <link>https://blog.ektagarg.com/posts/profiling-and-optimizing-go/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jan 2021 11:58:58 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.ektagarg.com/posts/profiling-and-optimizing-go/</guid>
      <description>Profiling A dynamic program analysis that measures space, time complexity, frequency and duration of function calls, usage of instructions.
Profiling is achieved by instrumenting either the program source code or its binary executable form using a tool called a profiler (or code profiler). Profilers may use a number of different techniques, such as event-based, statistical, instrumented, and simulation methods.
Profiling in Go One of the great things about Go is that it has really rich profiling tools included.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Golang: A Todo App using GIN</title>
      <link>https://blog.ektagarg.com/posts/todo-app-using-gin/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2020 02:01:58 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.ektagarg.com/posts/todo-app-using-gin/</guid>
      <description>Gin is a high-performance micro-framework that can be used to build web applications. It allows you to write middleware that can be plugged into one or more request handlers or groups of request handlers.
It is the most popular framework in Golang. Look at the picture above, this framework has the highest no. of stars on Github.com
Goals By the end of this tutorial, you will:
 Learn how to use Gin to create RESTful APIs (we will be creating a TODO application), and Understand the parts of a web application written in Go.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>