<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Blog by Ekta</title>
    <link>https://blog.ektagarg.com/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Blog by Ekta</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Feb 2021 02:01:58 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://blog.ektagarg.com/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>CDN: Content Delivery Network</title>
      <link>https://blog.ektagarg.com/posts/cdn/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Feb 2021 02:01:58 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.ektagarg.com/posts/cdn/</guid>
      <description>What is the challenge that CDN addresses? For eg: we have a software which has users from all around the world, but we don&amp;rsquo;t have servers all around the world and the experience that those users have due to that dynamic.
What is a CDN? It is a service that accelerates internet content delivery to make your website faster.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>HTTP2</title>
      <link>https://blog.ektagarg.com/posts/http2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Feb 2021 02:01:58 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.ektagarg.com/posts/http2/</guid>
      <description>How HTTP2.0 works?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Profiling and optimizing GO [PART-1]</title>
      <link>https://blog.ektagarg.com/posts/profiling-and-optimizing-go/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jan 2021 11:58:58 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.ektagarg.com/posts/profiling-and-optimizing-go/</guid>
      <description>Profiling A dynamic program analysis that measures space, time complexity, frequency and duration of function calls, usage of instructions.
Profiling is achieved by instrumenting either the program source code or its binary executable form using a tool called a profiler (or code profiler). Profilers may use a number of different techniques, such as event-based, statistical, instrumented, and simulation methods.
Profiling in Go One of the great things about Go is that it has really rich profiling tools included.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Slack bot using [Zapier &#43; Redash &#43; Google sheets &#43; Slack]</title>
      <link>https://blog.ektagarg.com/posts/slack-bot-using-zapier/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 09:01:58 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.ektagarg.com/posts/slack-bot-using-zapier/</guid>
      <description>What are we going to do?
Creating a slack bot that will post a message on a specific channel at a certain time (say, 9 am) about the total number of orders placed on your website in the last 24 hours.
Assumptions  Using slack for communication, organization of your work. Know how to write DB queries, I will be using redash for writing queries. Know the basics of google sheets.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tech talks 2020</title>
      <link>https://blog.ektagarg.com/posts/goodbye-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Dec 2020 09:01:58 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.ektagarg.com/posts/goodbye-2020/</guid>
      <description>This year has been a roller coaster ride for me, and I guess, for most people. Things were so uncertain. Even during this time of uncertainty, some of the tech communities have gone completely online and done a tremendous job of organizing conferences. This blog is about all the talks I gave at various conferences this year and all of them are related to Go.
Go One of the great things which I feel Go offers is clarity and ease-of-use.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How web applications work?</title>
      <link>https://blog.ektagarg.com/posts/webapps/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2020 16:08:56 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.ektagarg.com/posts/webapps/</guid>
      <description>You must be thinking that such a basic question doesn&amp;rsquo;t need an entire article. But as you will read, you&amp;rsquo;ll understand why this basic question do deserve an article.
Well, I asked this same question written above to a room full of programmers/developers. I could see the look of total contempt and amazement for asking such a basic question. But as I started getting answers from assembled technologies, I realised that the core understanding of how web apps work isn&amp;rsquo;t that simple.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Golang: A Todo App using GIN</title>
      <link>https://blog.ektagarg.com/posts/todo-app-using-gin/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2020 02:01:58 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.ektagarg.com/posts/todo-app-using-gin/</guid>
      <description>Gin is a high-performance micro-framework that can be used to build web applications. It allows you to write middleware that can be plugged into one or more request handlers or groups of request handlers.
It is the most popular framework in Golang. Look at the picture above, this framework has the highest no. of stars on Github.com
Goals By the end of this tutorial, you will:
 Learn how to use Gin to create RESTful APIs (we will be creating a TODO application), and Understand the parts of a web application written in Go.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>